Finding Aid for the Kango Takamura Paintings LSC.0433
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kango Takamura paintings
1942-1945
UCLA Library Special Collections
Takamura, Kango, 1895-1990
LSC.0433
0.5 linear feet (1 box and 2 oversize boxes)
Kango Takamura (1895-1990) was an photo retoucher for RKO Studios in Los Angeles when Pearl Harbor was attacked by the Japanese Imperial Navy. He was detained by the FBI in 1942 after offering to sell a motion-picture camera to a visiting Japanese general. He was interned at Santa Fe, New Mexico for several months and then moved to a camp at Manzanar, California, where he joined his wife, daughter, son-in-law and granddaughter. He remained at Manzanar with his family until 1945. While at Manzanar, Takamura depicted his surroundings in drawings and watercolors. He also worked as a camp sign-maker at Santa Fe and as curator for a small museum at Manzanar. After the war, he returned to Hollywood and worked at RKO Studios for another twenty-five years before retiring. The collection consists of 77 watercolor paintings produced during World War II while Kango Takamura was detained at the Santa Fe Internment Camp, New Mexico, and the Manzanar Internment Camp, California. Also included are paper mounts and one photographic reproduction of a painting.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kango Takamura, 1974.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9949622253606533
Biography
Kango Takamura was an Issei artist born in Kumamoto-ken, Japan in January of 1895. He immigrated to the United States when he was seventeen years old. Takamura spent ten years in Hawaii and then went to New York after becoming interested in the motion picture industry. After a short stay at the Paramount Studios offices in Long Island he moved to Hollywood. He was working as a photo retoucher for RKO Studios in Los Angeles when Pearl Harbor was attacked by the Japanese Imperial Navy. Takamura was detained by the FBI in 1942 after offering to sell a motion-picture camera to a visiting Japanese general. He was interned at Santa Fe, New Mexico for several months and then moved to a camp at Manzanar, California, where he joined his wife, daughter, son-in-law and granddaughter. He remained at Manzanar with his family until 1945. Takamura was not allowed to take photographs during his stays at Santa Fe and Manzanar but he depicted his surroundings in drawings and watercolors. He also worked as a camp sign-maker at Santa Fe and as curator for a small museum at Manzanar. When Takamura left Manzanar he returned to Hollywood and worked at RKO Studios for another twenty-five years before retiring. Takamura lived in Los Angeles until he passed away in January, 1990 at 94 years old.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of 77 watercolor paintings produced during World War II while Kango Takamura was detained at the Santa Fe Internment Camp, New Mexico, and the Manzanar Internment Camp, California. Also included are paper mounts and one photographic reproduction of a painting.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Santa Fe.
Manzanar.
The series names identify the place where the paintings in each series were produced.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Kango Takamura Paintings (76 items).
Watercolors.; Japanese American painters -- Archives.; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Santa Fe Internment Camp (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Takamura, Kango, 1895-1990 -- Archives; Manzanar War Relocation Center -- Pictorial works
- Santa Fe
  - Our pet hawk died, 1942 May 22.; (21 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper, matted) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    "Our pet hawk died on May 22. The following day Mr. Sato of Chula Vista died. But same day over 80 of us internees were released."
    Unsigned with Japanese characters.
  - Our guard became a spring baseball fan, n.d.; (21 × 28 cm. Watercolor and pencil on paper, matted) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "Our guard in the watch tower became a spring baseball fan at Santa Fe."
  - At evening I sketched this unusual cloud formation, 1942 May 31.; (25.5 × 37.5 cm. Watercolor on paper, matted) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    No caption.
    Signed.
  - Surprised guard on night watch at Santa Fe, n.d.; (27.5 × 42.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on heavy paper) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "His bald pate shined as bright as a full moon."
    [Also], Pencil and ink sketches of women in kimono verso.
  - Early birds, 1942 June 8.; (19 × 27.5 cm. Watercolor and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Unsigned.
  - Chow time at the mess hall, 1942 June 8.; (19 × 30 cm. Watercolor and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Relaxing after supper, 1942 June 8.; (21 × 29 cm. Watercolor and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Santa Fe's sunsets were beautiful, n.d.; (17.5 × 26.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Enjoying the recording music, 1942 June 8.; (20.5 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    "Mr. Murayama, Mr. Hoshimiya. Enjoying the recording music."
  - Dawn in the winter, n.d.; (20.5 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Santa Fe internment camp, n.d.; (20 × 29.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    "Santa Fe internment camp."
  - Panorama of Santa Fe internment center and mount, 1942 April 26.; (Painting 13 × 25 cm; mount 20 × 28 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper. Mount is card stock and rice paper with ink caption) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    No caption on painting.
    Signed with Japanese characters. Caption on mount reads: "Panorama of Santa Fe internment center. Drawn on writing paper - with anxiety - during early days when I was not sure that drawings of any kind were permitted."
  - Administration office, n.d.; (19.5 × 28 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    "Mr. Ohkado, Mr. Nozaki R., Mr. Kitagawa M."
  - A canteen for the convenience of Santa Fe internee, 1942 June 11.; (19.5 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    "Mr. Arai, Mr. Funahashi."
  - Sewing room, 1942 June 10.; (21.5 × 29.5 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    "Mr. Kamimura, Mr. Kamei, Mr. Kishi."
  - Barber shop, 1942 June 8.; (21 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - We made wooden clogs, 1942 June 10.; (21 × 30 cm. Watercolor and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - We made tubs, n.d.; (18.5 × 30 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - An adobe house inside our Santa Fe camp, n.d.; (17.5 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    "An adobe house inside our Santa Fe Camp."
  - Singing in the mess hall, n.d.; (21 × 30.5 cm. Watercolor and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Signed with Japanese characters.
  - Our umpire Mr. Higashikuze, n.d.; (20.5 × 29 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    "Mr. Higashikuze. Our umpire Mr. Higashikuze knew the rules but the players dint it. However we all had a good time."
  - This was the Santa Fe barrack no.5, 1942.; (21 × 21.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    "This was the Santa Fe barrack no.5 where I stayed."
  - A butane tank, 1942 June 8.; (20.5 × 29.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 19)
    "A butane tank was used to strike the gong that summoned us to mess hall. Santa Fe internment camp."
    Signed in pencil.
  - June 1942, 1942 June / May 23.; (19.5 × 29.5 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    "June 1942. Ending months of uncertainty, we were released from Santa Fe internment camp to return to our families at relocation centers. Everyone cheered as we left camp. Now there was hope we would return home."
  - Strange cloud, n.d.; (36 × 25.5 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    [Also], copy print with identical dimensions.
  - We stopped briefly at a small town, 1942 June 15.; (20.5 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    "We stopped briefly at a small town - Needles, they said. To our pleasant surprise, Japanese workers brought us boxes of food."
  - Mojave, California, 1942 June 15.; (19.5 × 27 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    "Mojave, Calif. We waited for our bus here for seven long hours in a desert windstorm - after we disembarked from the train."
  - Original mounts and titles, (Paper) (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Our roommates in barracks no. five, n.d.; (38.9 × 57.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper, matted. Source of title noted in pencil verso) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    "Mr. Okaski, Mr. Sugiyama, Mr. Tsuyuki, Mr. Hagio, Mr. Yamamoto, Mr. Tanaka, Mr. Hatori, Mr. Yamada, Mr. Musashi, Mr. Takamura."
- Manzanar
  - Making rice cakes, 1942 December 31.; (21 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper, matted) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Making rice cakes (mochi-tsuki). New Year custom. No 2 kitchen."
  - Mr. Hirozawa, n.d.; (27 × 34 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper, matted) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    "Mr. Hirozawa. The chemists work incessantly in search of a better method of extracting rubber. Here a chemist is preparing latex from guayule."
  - Some characteristics of guayule strains, n.d.; (19.5 × 25 cm. Watercolor [?] and ink on paper, matted) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    "Some characteristics of guayule strains."
  - First successful growing of guayule, 1942 October 19.; (20 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper, matted) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "The first successful growing of -- guayule rubber plant cuttings."
  - Progress after one year, 1943 May 14.; (22 × 32 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper and inset black and white photograph, matted) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    "Progress after one year. The mess hall line."
    With inset photo caption: "Wall painting by Takamura."
  - Mr. Akaboshi, 1943.; (25.5 × 36 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper, matted) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    "Rooted cuttings are transplanted to milk cartons and then to the field. Transplanting is done carefully and speedily by hand of the experimenters. Mr. Akaboshi."
  - Manzanar High School commencement of 1944, (23.5 × 41.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    "Manzanar High School commencement of 1944. Our democratic country has people representing all nation[s] -- Mr. Ralph P. Merritt."
  - Untitled view of camp street, [1944?].; (24.5 × 39 cm. Watercolor on paper) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Keeping the camp clean and tidy, (37.5 × 51 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - A huge blender, (37 × 27.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    "A huge blender speedily stirring gallons of water mixed with chopped guayule, forces rubber out of the wood. This is a mechanical method which has been proved most efficient in extracting rubber from guayule shrubs."
  - Mr. Nishimura, n.d.; (26.5 × 36.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    "Mr. Nishimura. Analysis of the plant extracts is one of many research works which are carried out by the chemists. Here a chemist is working with a special apparatus for the determination of nitrogen."
  - Easter sunrise service, 1944 April 9.; (36 × 50.5 cm. Watercolor on paper) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    "Easter sunrise service."
  - Saturday afternoon looking south from block 8, 1943 May.; (31.5 × 50.5 cm. Watercolor on paper) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mr. Hata, 1943.; (26.5 × 37 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    "Propagation of plants by cutting method has been succeeded for the first time. Guayule cuttings are treated with a phytohormone before setting in a flat."
  - Home sweet home, 1942 June 16.; (21 × 28 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 24)
    "Home sweet home for men coming home to Manzanar from [feet] furlough."
  - First impression of Manzanar, 1942 June.; (21.5 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    "First impression of Manzanar."
  - I visited Dr. Carter today, 1942 October 8.; (21.5 × 29.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    "I visited Dr. Carter today because school has opened and I am to make drawings of class scenes. It seemed a hundred people were rushing in and out of her office. All over her desk; the telephone rang all the time."
  - Its nap time, n.d.; (22 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    "It's nap time, but there's more noise than rest. The youngsters wriggle around, won't lie still. The teachers look exhausted. The scam in the foreground turns around: 'Hiya popa, watcha doin?' Rest time in the nursery class."
  - Children in the classroom, n.d.; (20 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Teacher, I know, n.d.; (22 × 26.5 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 29)
    "'Teacher, I know - ' At the other end of the same barrack. First graders of Miss Joh sit awkwardly about the mess table. A question has just been asked. Little Hiroshi, on the end slowly lifts his hand 'Teacher, I know.'"
  - Did you ever see such individual dress attire?, (21 cm × 28 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 30)
    "Did you ever see such individual dress attire? This is a high school gym class I ran into on the dusty field next to block 7. Facing each other in a circle, they would clap their hands, say something, laugh. Off in the corner another class came dashing by in a cloud of dust. But school is wonderful."
  - A cooking class, 1942.; (22 × 30 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 31)
    "A cooking class. What vitamins do potatoes have? Miss Smith teaches her girls in what used to be the kitchen of mess hall 7."
  - Gee, that Angleworm's my name, n.d.; (22.5 × 29.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 32)
    "'Gee, that angleworm's my name.' said Haruo, slouched over the classroom steps as Mr. Lamphere showed his shorthand pupils how to write their name in the Gregg manner."
  - The boys in the woodcarving class, n.d.; (21.5 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 33)
    "The boys in the woodcarving class of Mr. Bouche were being praised for their good work that day. The teacher was kept very busy showing his pupils how to hold the chisel."
  - Manzanar High School, 1942 October 8.; (21 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 34)
    "Manzanar High School. Studies took on great importance in these barrack classrooms. This was a day before the week-end holiday."
  - Roll call is taken, 1942 October 8.; (21.5 × 28 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 35)
    "Roll call is taken. This was first day of school he study hall. Converted from a former mess hall, resounded with laughter as Mr. Vanderjagt aide would call a name and a squeaky soprano would respond 'Here,' only to be followed by an off-pitch bass 'Heah.' Unsigned.
  - Students hurry to the classes, 1943 Feb.; (20 × 30.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 36)
    "Students hurry to the classes as the bell rings on this foggy morning."
  - Approximately 200 students graduated, 1943 July 3.; (22 × 30.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 37)
    "Approximately 200 students graduated at second Manzanar High School commencement."
  - More Mochi at Manzanar, n.d.; (18.5 × 27 cm. Watercolor, pencil, and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Making rice cakes, n.d.; (21 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 39)
    "Making rice cakes. New Year custom."
  - Pounding the Mochi, (21.5 × 28 cm. Watercolor, pencil, and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Mochi-Tsuki, n.d.; (20.5 × 28 cm. Watercolor, pencil, and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 41)
    "Mochi-Tsuki."
  - Mochi-Tsuki, Making rice cakes, n.d.; (19.5 × 25.5 cm. Watercolor, pencil, and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 42)
    "Mochi-Tsuki. Making rice cakes. New Year custom."
  - Clothing allowance, 1942 October 12.; (19 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 43)
    "Clothing allowance."
  - Bainbridge people, 1942 February 24.; (21.5 × 30 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 44)
    "Bainbridge people bidding farewell as they leave for Minnedoka relocation camp."
  - Residents installed plaster boards, 1942 November 1.; (19.5 × 29 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 45)
    "Residents installed plaster boards inside barracks. This was the room of Mr. and Mrs. Kurahashi."
  - At leisure on New Year's afternoon, 1943 January 1.; (22 × 34.5 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - She is knitting. He is carving, 1943 February 18.; (19 × 27 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 47)
    "She is knitting. He is carving wood. They enjoy their hobbies."
  - Snow in January 1944, 1944 January 6.; (21.5 × 30.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 48)
    "Snow in January 1944, block 35 at Manzanar."
  - Oil for the barracks, 1944 February 22.; (22 × 33 cm. Watercolor on paper) (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - The residents transformed dusty semi-arid land, 1942 October 26.; (20 × 29 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 50)
    "The residents transformed dusty semi-arid land into green truck forms, growing vegetable crops of all kinds. I sketched this scene of workers harvesting large, ripe, sweet watermelons."
  - Manzanar farm, 1942 October 26.; (17 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 51)
    "Manzanar Farm."
  - Farm workers, 1942 October 26.; (22 × 28.5 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 52)
    "Farm workers harvest a crop of Manzanar grown okra."
  - Guayule shrub and leaf types, (20 × 25 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 53)
    "Guayule shrub and leaf types. Some of the leaf types can be used to distinguish one strain from another."
  - A biologist hybridizes, n.d.; (24 × 35 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper) (Box 2, Folder 54)
    "A biologist hybridizes Guayule trying to produce plants superior in quality than those existing now."
  - After the rain an abandoned baby cart, 1945 October 30.; (22.5 × 35 cm. Watercolor on paper) (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - The Manzanar auditorium, 1944 May 24.; (16 × 29.5 cm. Watercolor, ink, and pencil on paper) (Box 2, Folder 56)
    "The Manzanar auditorium and community hall nears completion."
  - Original mounts and titles, (Paper) (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Untitled winter landscape, (38.5 × 51 cm. Watercolor and ink on paper, matted) (Box 3, Folder 2)